Thank you.
Discuss order, converse about order,
and I thought perhaps we could begin with that today,
if that's agreeable with you.
I think we were talking about freedom,
responsibility and relationship.
And before we go any further,
we thought we would...
talk over together this question of order.
What is order in freedom?
As one observes all over the world,
there is such extraordinary disorder.
Oh yes.
Outwardly and inwardly.
One wonders why there is such disorder.
You go to India and you see
the streets filled with people,
bursting with population.
And you see also so many sects,
so many gurus, so many teachers,
so many...
...content.
Contradictory lies.
Such misery.
And you come to Europe,
there is little more order,
but you see when you penetrate the superficial order,
there is equal disorder.
And you come to this country,
and you know what it
is like better than I do,
there is complete disorder.
You may be... drive very carefully,
but go behind...
...the façade of so-called order,
and you see chaos.
Not only in personal relationship,
but sexually, morally,
and there is so much corruption.
All governments are corrupt,
some more, some less.
But this whole phenomenon
of disorder,
how has it come about?
Is it the fault of the religions
that have said,
do this and don't do that?
And now they are revolting against all that.
Yes.
Is it governments are so corrupt
that nobody has any trust
in governments?
Is it there is such corruption in business,
nobody wants to look at it even?
Any intelligent man,
any man who is really serious,
and you look at family life,
there is such disorder.
So, taking the whole phenomena of disorder,
why is there such disorder?
What has brought it about?
Doesn't it appear that there is a sort of
necessary, almost built-in progression
in terms of the way we mentioned necessity earlier?
Once order, so conceived,
is superimposed upon an existing situation,
not only does it not effect
what is hoped for,
but it creates a new situation...
Of course.
...which we think requires a new approach.
And the new approach is still the superimposition.
Like the Communists are doing in Russia and China,
they have imposed order,
what they call order,
on a disordered mind.
Yes.
And therefore there is a revolt.
So, looking at all this,
it is very interesting,
looking at all this phenomenon of disorder,
what is order then?
Is order something imposed,
order as in the military,
on the soldier, imposed order,
a discipline which is a conformity,
suppression, imitation,
is order conformity?
Not in the sense if it is artificially imposed, yes.
In any sense.
If I conform to an order,
I am creating disorder.
Yes, yes, I understand what you mean.
In our use of the word conform,
we sometimes mean by it
a natural relation between the nature of a thing
and the activities that are proper to it
or belong to it.
But then that use of the word conform
is not the use that is usual
and the one that we are concerned in here.
No. No.
So, is order conformity?
Is order imitation?
Is order acceptance, obedience?
Or because we have conformed,
because we have obeyed,
because we have accepted,
we have created disorder?
Because discipline,
in the ordinary accepted sense of that word,
is to conform.
Yes, we say in English, don't we,
to someone who appears to be undisciplined
or who in fact is undisciplined,
we say, straighten up.
Straighten up, yes.
The images that we use to refer to that correction
are always rigid, aren't they?
Yes.
Yes, yes.
So that authority,
whether the communist authority of the few
or the authority of the priest
or the authority of someone who says,
I know and you don't know,
that is one of the factors
that has produced disorder.
And one of the factors of this disorder
is our lack of real culture.
We are very sophisticated,
very so-called civilised,
in the sense we are clean,
we have bathrooms,
we have better food and all that,
but inwardly we are not cultured.
We are not healthy, whole human beings.
The inner fragmentation spills out
into our operations externally.
So, unless we understand disorder,
the nature of disorder,
the structure of disorder,
we can never find out what is order.
Out of the understanding of disorder comes order.
Not first seek order
and then impose that order,
and then that order and disorder.
I don't know if I am making myself clear.
Yes, I do.
I am thinking as you are speaking
of the phenomenon
in the world of study
and the world of teaching and learning
as we understand them conventionally.
I have noticed in our conversations
that you always suggest
that we study some dysfunction.
We are never invited really to do that.
We are given the notion
that the thing to study
is the principle involved.
The argument for that, of course,
is that one refers to health
in order to understand disease.
But then the reference to health,
when that is said,
is received purely conceptually.
Quite, quite.
And so what we are studying is now...
Is a concept rather than the actuality,
than the what is.
And we slip out...
Yes, quite.
...of the true task.
There is a difficulty in grasping the suggestion
that we study the disorder...
Disorder.
...simply because disorder
by its own condition
is without an ordering principle.
Quite, quite, quite.
Therefore it sounds, when it comes out,
as though I am being asked to study
something that is unstudiable.
But to the contrary...
On the contrary?
Yes.
Yes, now I will stop.
Go ahead.
On the contrary,
you were about to say something.
there must be an understanding of disorder.
Why it has come about.
Yes.
One of the factors, sir, is, I think, basically,
that thought is matter,
and thought, by its very nature, is fragmentary.
Thought divides the me and the not me,
we and the my country and your country,
my ideas and your ideas,
my religion and your... and so on.
The very movement of thought is divisive.
Because thought is the response of memory,
the response of thought,
the response of experience, which is the past.
And unless we really go into this question
very, very deeply,
the movement of thought
and the movement of disorder.
That seems to me to be a key word there,
for my understanding, in listening to you,
movement here,
to study the movement of disorder,
would seem to me to take it a step deeper
than the phrase to study disorder.
With the word movement, we are dealing with act.
Movement.
Exactly.
The career of disorder.
Yes.
If that is what we are directed upon,
then I think the objection
that the study of disorder,
the study of disorder is to undertake
an impossible pursuit,
is not made with any foundation.
That objection loses its force
precisely at the point when one says,
no, no, it is not disorder as a concept
that we are dealing with here.
It is the movement of it.
It is its own career, it is its passage,
it is the whole corruption of the act as such.
Yes, exactly.
I keep on saying this
business about act all the time,
and perhaps it seems repetitious.
Oh, that is absolutely right.
But, you know, hardly ever is that taken seriously.
I know, sir.
By our species.
Of course, the animals are on to that
from the beginning.
But we don't.
No.
You see that we deal with concepts,
not with what is, actually what is,
rather than discuss formulas,
concepts and ideas,
what is, is disorder.
And that disorder is spreading all over the world.
It is a movement, it is a living disorder.
It isn't disorder which is dead,
it is a living thing, moving, corrupting, destroying.
Yes, exactly. Exactly.
So...
It takes, as you pointed out so often,
it takes an extreme concentration of attention
to follow movement.
And there is a rebellion in us against following movement,
which perhaps lies in our disaffection
with the intuition that we have
that transition is unintelligent.
Quite, quite.
And we don't want that.
We can't stand the thought that there is something
that is unintelligible.
And so we just will not make that active attention.
Quite.
So it is like sitting
on the bank of a river
and watching the waters go by.
You can't alter the water.
You can't change the substance
or the movement of the water.
In the same way this movement of disorder
is part of us and is flowing outside of us.
So one has to look at it.
And there is no confusion in the act at all.
Obviously not.
It is...
First of all, sir, let's
go into it very, very carefully.
What is the factor of disorder?
Disorder means contradiction.
Yes, and conflict.
Contradiction. This opposed to that.
Right.
Or the duality.
This opposed to that.
The contention between two things to be mutually exclusive.
Yes.
And what brings about
this duality and the conflict?
Is there a duality at all?
Certainly not in act there is not a duality.
That simply couldn't be.
There certainly could be said,
not even with respect, don't you think,
to thought itself and its operation,
that there is a dualism.
But the duality, of course,
is present in terms of distinction,
but not in terms of division.
Division, that's right.
Not in terms of division.
Yes, yes, I follow.
I mean, after all, there is man, woman,
black and white and so on.
But is there an opposite to violence?
Yes, I am listening very intently.
Or only violence?
Yes.
But we have created the opposite.
Thought has created the opposite as non-violence.
And then the conflict between the two.
The non-violence is an abstraction of the what is.
And thought has done that.
Exactly. Yesterday I had a difficult time in class
over this.
I made the remark that vice
is not the opposite of virtue.
Virtue is not the opposite of vice.
And somehow I just couldn't, it seems,
communicate that because of the insistence
on the part of the students
to deal with the problem purely in terms
of a conceptual structure.
That's...
You see, sir, I don't know if
you want to go into it now,
if it is the right occasion.
From ancient Greece, you must know,
measurement was necessary to them.
Measurement.
And the whole of the Western civilisation
is based on measurement.
Which is thought.
This is certainly true in continuous practice.
It is certainly true.
And the irony of it is that an historian
looking at the works of the great Greek thinkers
would turn around and say at this point,
well, now, just wait a minute,
and we would say some things about Aristotle and Plato
that would suggest that no, no, no, no,
there's a much more organic grasp of things
than simply approaching it in a slide rule way.
But that doesn't come to terms with what you're saying.
No, I...
Sir...
Right.
You can see what is happening in the world,
in the Western world.
Technology, commercialism and consumerism
is the highest activity that's going on now.
Exactly.
Which is based on measurement.
Yes, it is. Oh, yes.
Which is thought.
Now, look at it, hold it that minute,
and you'll see something rather odd taking place.
The East, especially India,
India exploded over the East...
Yes.
...in a different sense.
They said measurement is illusion.
To find the immeasurable,
the measurement must come to an end.
I'm putting it very crudely and quickly.
No, but it seems to me
that you're putting it precisely well
with respect to this concern we have with act.
Yes.
It's not crude.
It's very interesting because I've watched it.
In the West, technology, commercialism and consumerism
– God, saviour, church, all that's outside,
is a plaything.
And you just play with it on Saturday and Sunday,
and by the rest of you do.
Yes.
And you go to India and you see this.
The word ma is to measure, Sanskrit.
You must...
Oh, yes, right.
And they said reality is immeasurable.
Go into it, see the beauty of it.
Yes, oh, yes, I follow.
So the measurement can never find...
A mind that is measuring,
or a mind that is caught in measurement,
can never find truth.
I'm putting it that way,
they don't put it that way,
I'm putting it.
So they said to find the real, the immense,
measurement must end.
But they use thought
as a means to...
as thought must be controlled, they said.
Yes.
You follow?
Yes, I do.
So in order to find the immeasurable,
you must control thought.
And to control...
Who is the controller of thought?
Another fragment of thought.
I don't know if you follow.
Oh, I follow you perfectly. Yes, I do.
So they use measurement
as a means of measurement.
Yes.
And therefore they could never go beyond it.
They were caught in an illusion of some other kind,
but it's still the product of thought.
I don't know if I...
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
What flashed over my mind as you were speaking
was the incredible irony of
their having,
right in front of them,
I'm thinking now of the
Brihadaranyaka Upanishad,
this profound statement,
that is full,
meaning anything that I think is over there,
that's full,
this that I've divided off from that,
this is full,
from fullness,
to fullness issues forth.
And then the next line,
if fullness is taken away from the full,
fullness indeed still remains.
Now, there's reading that, you see,
but if they approach it
in the manner that you've so well described,
they haven't read it,
in the sense of attended to what's being said,
because it's the total...
it's the total rejection of that statement
that would be involved in thought control.
Yes, of course.
Yes.
You see, that's what I'm trying to get at.
You see,
thought has divided
the world physically
– America, India, Russia, China,
you follow? –
divided the world.
Thought has fragmented
the activities of man,
the businessman, the artist, the politician,
the beggar, you follow?
Fragmented that.
Yes, yes.
Thought has created a society
based on this fragmentation,
and thought has created the gods,
the saviours, the Jesuses,
the Christs, the Krishnas, the Buddha.
And those are all measurable,
in the sense you must become like the Christ,
or you must be good.
All sanctioned by a culture
which is based on measurement.
Once you start with forecasts,
as we have classically,
then we're going to necessarily move
to five, six, seven, four hundred, four thousand,
an indefinite division.
And all in the interest,
it is claimed, of clarity.
All in the interest of clarity.
So unless we understand
the movement of thought,
we cannot possibly understand disorder.
It is thought that has produced disorder.
Sounds contradictory, but it is so.
Because thought is fragmentary.
Thought is time.
And as long as we understand
as long as we are functioning within that field,
there must be disorder.
Which is, each fragment is working for itself,
in opposition to other fragments.
I, a Christian, am in opposition to the Hindu,
but love and goodness and all the rest of it...
I love him so much,
I want to see him saved,
so I will go out
and bring him into the fold.
I will come over to my camp.
Yes, yes, yes.
So, one of the, probably the basic cause of disorder
is the fragmentation of thought.
I was told the other day
that in a certain culture,
thought means the outside.
Yes.
That's very interesting.
When they use the word outside,
they use the word thought.
And we think it's inside.
That's the whole... You follow?
How marvellous, how marvellous.
So thought is always outside.
Whether you can say I am inwardly thinking.
Thought has divided the outer and the inner.
So to understand this whole contradiction,
measurement, time,
the division, the fragmentation, the chaos, the disorder,
one must really go into this question of
what is thought, what is thinking?
Can the mind,
which has been so conditioned in fragments,
in fragmentation,
can that mind observe
this whole movement of disorder,
not fragmentarily...
No, but the movement itself.
Movement itself.
Movement itself, yes.
But that's what's so terrifying,
to look at that whole thing,
that movement.
It's interesting that
you've asked this question
in a way that keeps boring in,
because measure is...
and I'm going to put something now
in a very concise elliptical way,
is possibility,
which is infinitely divisible
and only comes to an end
with an act.
And as long as I remain
divided against act,
I regard myself as a very deep thinker.
I'm sitting back,
exploring alternatives
which are completely imaginary, illusory.
And in the business world,
men are paid extremely high salaries
to come up with what is called a new concept.
Yes, a new concept.
And it's called by its right name, of course,
but it isn't regarded in...
it isn't regarded correctly as to its nature.
It isn't understood as to what's being said.
That brings up the point which is,
measurement means comparison.
Yes.
Our society and our civilisation
is based on comparison.
From childhood in the school
to college and university,
it is comparative.
That's right.
And comparison between
intelligence and dullness,
between the tall and the black,
white and purple and all the rest of it.
Comparison of success, in success.
And look at also our religions.
The priest, the bishop,
you follow?
The hierarchical outlook,
ultimately the pope or the archbishop.
The whole structure is based on that,
comparison.
Comparison, which is measurement,
which is essentially thought.
Yes.
The Protestants complain about the Catholic hierarchy,
and yet their scripture, their bible,
is what some Catholics call their paper pope.
Paper pope.
Of course.
Yes.
With the very rejection of something,
something takes its place
which becomes even more divisive.
Yes.
So is it possible
to look without measurement,
that is, without comparison?
Is it possible to live a life
– life, living, acting, laughing,
the whole life living, crying,
without a shadow of comparison coming into it?
Sir, I am not boasting,
I am just telling a fact.
I have never compared myself with anybody.
That is a most remarkable thing.
Most remarkable thing.
I have never thought about it,
even to say somebody is much cleverer than me.
Somebody much more brilliant,
so intelligent,
somebody greater spiritually.
It didn't enter.
Therefore I say to myself,
is measurement, comparison, imitation,
are they not the major factors of disorder?
I have had a very good conversation
with a very long thought
about what you said a few conversations ago
about when you were a boy
and you never accepted the distinctions
that were employed in a dividing way.
Oh, of course, of course.
And within the social order.
And I had to think about my own growing up
and accept the fact that I did accept this distinction
in terms of division,
but I didn't do it with nature.
But that set up a conflict in me.
Of course.
Because I couldn't understand
how it could be the case
that I am natural
as a being in the world
but I am not somehow related to things
the way things are in what we call nature.
Then it suddenly occurred to me later
that in thinking that way
I was already dividing myself off from nature
and I'd never get out of that problem.
No.
And the thing came to me some years ago
with a tremendous flash.
When I was in Bangkok in a temple garden
and of an early morning
I was taking a walk
and my eye was drawn
to a globule of dew resting on a lotus leaf.
And it was perfectly spherical.
And I said,
where's the base?
How can it be stable?
Why doesn't it roll off?
Why doesn't it...
By the time I got
to the end of my whys
I was worn out
and so I took a deep breath
and I said, now, shut up.
And just keep quiet and look.
And I saw that
each maintained its own nature
in this marvellous nature
in this harmony
without any confusion at all.
And I was just still.
Quite.
Just still.
I think that's something of what you mean
about the fact that that was a fact.
Just remain with the fact.
Look at the fact.
Quite.
That marvellous globule
on that leaf
is the fact.
Yes.
Is the act.
Is what is done.
Isn't that what...
It's good.
Right. Yes.
Sir, from this arises
can one educate
a student
to live a life
of non-comparison?
Bigger car, lesser car.
You follow?
Yes.
Dull, you are clever, I am not clever.
What happens if I don't compare at all?
Will I become dull?
On the contrary.
I am only dull,
I know I am dull only through comparison.
If I don't compare,
I don't know what I am.
Then I begin from there.
Yes.
The world becomes infinitely accessible.
Oh, then the whole thing becomes
extraordinarily different.
There is no competition,
there is no anxiety,
there is no conflict with each other.
This is why you use
the word total often, isn't it?
In order to express that there is no...
there is nothing in the world
that is being drawn out
from one condition to the other.
There is no...
there is no link there,
there is no bridge there.
Totally disordered.
Totally ordered.
Absolutely.
Yes, and you use the word absolute often,
which terrifies many people today.
So, after all, mathematics is order.
Oh, yes.
And in the highest form of mathematical investigation,
you must have a mind that is totally orderly.
The marvellous thing about math too is that
whereas it is the study of quantity,
you don't make passage from one integer to another
by two getting larger.
It stops at two.
Two and a half is no more two.
Somehow that is the case.
Yes.
But a child, when he has taught mathematics,
is never introduced to that,
that I have ever heard of.
You see, sir, our teaching and everything is so absurd.
Is it possible, sir,
to observe this movement of disorder
with a mind
that is disorderly itself,
and say, can this mind observe disorder,
this mind which is already in a state of disorder?
So disorder isn't out there.
No.
But in here.
Now,
can the mind observe that disorder
without introducing a factor
of an observer who is orderly?
Who will superimpose.
Yes.
Therefore observe perceived disorder
without the perceiver.
I don't know if...
Yes.
Yes, you are making sense.
That is, sir,
to understand disorder
we think
an orderly mind is necessary.
As over against the disorderly mind.
Disorder.
But the mind itself has created this disorder,
which is thought and all the rest of it.
So can the mind
not look at disorder out there,
but the maker of disorder which is in here?
Which is itself, the very mind,
as disorderly.
Mind itself is disorderly.
Yes.
But as soon as that is stated conceptually...
No, no, no. Concepts are finished.
Yes. But we are using words.
We are using words to communicate.
Exactly.
And what I am concerned with,
just for a second,
is what are we going to say
when we hear the statement
that it is the disordered mind
that keeps proliferating disorder,
but it is that disordered mind that must see.
Yes.
That must see.
I am going to show you.
You will see in a minute what takes place.
Yes.
Now, disorder is not outside of me,
disorder is inside of me.
That is a fact.
Because the mind is disorderly,
all its activities must be disorderly.
And the activities of disorder
is proliferating or is moving in the world.
Now,
can this mind observe itself
without introducing the factor of an orderly mind,
which is the opposite?
I don't know...
Yes, it is.
The opposite is...
Of course it is the opposite.
So can it observe
without the observer,
who is the opposite?
I don't know.
That is the question.
It...
Now, watch it, sir,
if you are really interested in it.
I am. I am deeply interested in it.
You will see.
The observer is the observed.
The observer who says,
I am orderly
and I must put order in disorder.
Generally what takes place.
But the observer
is the factor of disorder.
Because the observer is the past,
is the factor of division.
Where there is division
there is not only conflict but disorder.
You could see, sir,
it happening actually in the world.
I mean, all this problem of energy,
all this problem of war,
peace and all that,
can all be solved absolutely
when people,
when there are not separate governments,
sovereign armies,
and say, look,
let's solve this problem altogether,
for God's sake.
We are human beings.
This earth is meant for us to live on,
not Arabs and Israelis
and America and Russia.
It is our earth.
And it is round.
Yes.
But we will never do that
because our minds are so conditioned
to live in disorder,
to live in conflict.
And vocation is given a religious description
in terms of the task
of cleaning up the disorder
with my idea of order.
Your idea of order
is the fact that has produced disorder.
Exactly.
So it brings up a question, sir,
which is very interesting.
Can the mind observe itself
without the observer?
Because the observer is the observed.
Disorder, the observer
who says, I will bring order,
in disorder,
that observer itself is a fragment of disorder.
Yes.
Therefore it can never bring about order.
So can the mind be aware of itself
as a movement of disorder,
not trying to correct it,
not trying to justify it,
not trying to shape it,
just to observe?
Yes.
I said previously,
to observe sitting on the banks of a river
and watch the waters go by,
you see,
I mean, then you see much more.
But if you are in the middle of it,
swimming, you will see nothing.
I have never forgot
that it was when I stopped questioning
and I stood before that droplet of dew
on the leaf
that everything changed.
Totally.
And what you say is true.
Once something like that happens,
there isn't a regression from it.
Oh, no.
Sir, it is not once, it is...
Forever.
Yes.
It is not an incident that took place,
my life is not an incident,
it is a movement.
Exactly.
And in that movement
I observe this movement of disorder.
And therefore the mind itself is disorderly,
and how can that disorderly, chaotic, contradictory,
absurd little mind bring about order?
It can't.
Therefore a new factor is necessary.
And the new factor is
to observe,
to perceive, to see,
without the perceiver.
To perceive without the perceiver.
Because the perceiver is the perceived.
Yes.
If you once grasp that,
then you see everything without the perceived.
You don't bring in your personality,
your ego, your selfishness.
You say, disorder is the factor which is in me,
not out there.
The perceiver is the factor
which is in me.
And the politicians trying to bring about order,
when they are themselves so corrupt.
You follow, sir?
How can they bring order?
It is impossible.
It is one long series of palliatives.
And that is what is happening in the world,
where the politicians are ruling the world.
In Delhi, from Washington, wherever it is,
it is the same pattern being repeated.
Living a chaotic, corrupt life,
you try to bring order in the world.
It is childish.
So, that is why
transformation of the mind
is not your mind or my mind.
It is the mind.
The human mind.
Or the mind trying to order itself,
not even that.
How can a blind man trying to bring about colour?
And he says, well, that is grey.
You follow? It has no meaning.
So, can the mind observe this disorder
in itself,
without the observer who has created disorder?
Sir, this brings a very simple thing.
To look
at a tree, at a woman, at a mountain,
at a bird, or a sheet of water
with a light on it, the beauty of it,
to look without the seer.
Because the moment the seer comes in,
the observer comes in, he divides.
And the division is all right
as long as it is descriptive.
But when you are living,
that division is destructive.
I don't know if you have any other...
Yes, what was running through
my mind was this continuous propaganda
that we hear about the techniques
that are available to still the mind.
But that requires a stiller to do the stilling.
And so that is absolutely...
I am using your words, absolutely and totally...
Yes, absolutely.
...out of any possibility of attaining...
But yet, you see, that
is what the gurus are doing.
Yes, yes, I do understand.
The imported gurus and the native gurus
are doing this.
They are really destroying people.
You follow, sir?
We will talk about it when it occasionally arises.
What we are now concerned is measurement,
which is the whole movement of commercialism,
consumerism, technology,
is now the pattern of the world.
Begun in the West,
and made more and more
and more perfect in the West,
and that is spreading all over the world.
Go to the smallest little town in India
or anywhere, the same pattern being repeated.
And the village you go,
and they are so miserable and happy,
one meal a day, starved.
But it is still within that pattern.
And the governments are trying to solve
this problem separately.
You follow? France by itself, Russia by itself.
It is a human problem,
therefore it has to be approached
with a Washington mind,
or a London mind, or a Moscow mind,
with a mind that is human, that says,
look, this is our problem,
and for God's sake, let's get together and solve it.
Which means care,
which means accepting responsibility
for every human being.
So, let's come back, as we said,
order comes only
with the understanding of disorder.
In that there is no superimposition,
in that there is no conflict,
in that there is no suppression.
When you suppress, you react,
you know all that business.
So it is totally a different kind of movement, order.
And that order
is real virtue.
Because without virtue, there is no order.
There is gangsterism.
Politically or any other way,
religiously,
but without virtue.
Virtue being conduct.
The flowering in goodness every day,
it is not a theory,
it actually takes place
when you live that way.
You know,
the hexagram in the I Ching called conduct
is also translated treading.
Treading.
Meaning a movement.
A movement.
Of course.
And that's a vastly different understanding
of the usual notion of conduct.
Of...
Yes, but I understand from what you've said
that your use of the word conduct as virtue,
as order,
is precisely oriented to act,
move.
Yes, sir.
Yes.
You see, a man who acts out of disorder
is creating more disorder.
The politician.
Look at his life, sir.
Ambitious, greedy, seeking power, position.
Running for election.
Election, all the rest of it.
And he is the man that's
going to create order in the world.
The tragedy of it, and we accept it.
You follow?
Yes, we believe it's inevitable.
We do.
And therefore we are irresponsible.
Because he didn't, he didn't, and I didn't.
Yes, yes.
Because we accept disorder in our life.
I don't accept disorder in my life.
I want to live an orderly life,
which means I must understand disorder.
And where there is order,
the brain functions much better.
There is a miracle here, isn't there?
Absolutely. That is the miracle.
There is a miracle here.
As soon as I grab...
grasp the movement of disorder...
The mind grasps.
Yes.
Behold, there is order.
That's just it, sir.
That's truly miraculous.
Perhaps it's the one and only miracle.
Well, there are other miracles, but I'm just...
I mean, in the deepest sense of the word,
all of them would have to be related to that,
or we wouldn't have any
of them, is what I meant.
The real heart, the real core...
That's why, sir, relationship,
communication,
responsibility, freedom,
and this freedom from disorder
is a great sense of beauty in it,
you know, a life that is beautiful,
a life that is really flowering in goodness.
Unless we create,
bring about such human beings,
the world will go to pot.
Yes.
This is what's happening.
And I feel it's my responsibility.
To me, that I'm passionate about.
It's my responsibility
to see that when I talk to you,
you understand it, you live it,
you function, move in that way.
Yes.
I come back to this attention thing.
The enormous emphasis that you've made
on staying totally attentive to this.
I think I begin to understand something of the phenomenon,
of what happens when a person begins to think
that they're taking seriously what you're saying.
I didn't say begins to take it seriously.
They think they're beginning to.
As a matter of fact, they begin
to watch themselves lean in to it.
But of course nothing's started yet.
But something very strange happens in the mind
when this notion that I'm leaning in,
I start to get terribly afraid.
I become terribly fearful of something.
Next time, could we discuss fear?
You know, sir, there is...
Subtitles by the Amara.org community